Guide to the Thomas Hardy Collection
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Thomas Hardy collection
1873-1989
GEN MSS 307
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
1.80
7 boxes
Autograph letters, signed, from Thomas Hardy to J. M. Barrie, Arthur Locker, Charles S. Prideaux, and others, with letters from his wives, Emma Lavinia Gifford Hardy and Florence Emily Hardy; and writings by Hardy, including an autograph manuscript draft of his novel Far from the Madding Crowd and typescript proofs of a short story, Spectre of the Real. Also includes a photograph of Hardy.
Hardy, Thomas, 1840-1928
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Ongoing collection of documents acquired by gift and purchase from various sources. Type of accession (gift or purchase) and date of acquisition is noted in the collection contents. For further information, consult the appropriate curator.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Existence and Location of Copies
Several items are available on microfilm. Consult Public Services staff.
Associated Materials
See also Richard L. Purdy Collection of Thomas Hardy, GEN MSS 111.
Scope and Contents
Autograph letters, signed, from Thomas Hardy to J. M. Barrie, Arthur Locker, Charles S. Prideaux, and others, with letters from his wives, Emma Lavinia Gifford Hardy and Florence Emily Hardy; and writings by Hardy, including an autograph manuscript draft of his novel Far from the Madding Crowd and typescript proofs of a short story, Spectre of the Real. Also includes a photograph of Hardy.
Arrangement
Organized in four series: I. Correspondence, 1876-1929. II. Writings, 1873-1919. III. Other Materials, 1889-1920. IV. Additions Since July 1997, 1885-1989.
Biographical / Historical
Thomas Hardy, English novelist and poet.
Authors, English -- 19th century -- Archives; Photographs; Barrie, J. M. (James Matthew), 1860-1937; Hardy, Emma Lavinia Gifford, 1840-1912; Hardy, Florence Emily, 1879-1937; Hardy, Thomas, 1840-1928; Locker, Arthur, 1828-1893; Prideaux, Charles S.
- Correspondence, 1876–1929; Series I
  - Letters by Emma Lavinia Gifford Hardy, 1907
    - Autograph letter, signed, to Mrs. Perkins, Max Gate, Dorchester, 1907 January 29 (Box 1)
      Immediate Source of Acquisition
      Purchase, 1995.
  - Letters by Florence Emily Hardy, 1922–1929
    - Autograph letter, signed, to [Gwen John], Max Gate, Dorchester, 1922 December 10 (Box 1)
      Purchase, 1996.
    - Autograph letter, signed, to A. Edward Norton (Box 1)
      Related Materials
      See: Series II, Box 2, folder 49
    - Autograph letter, signed, to Mrs. Perkins, Max Gate, Dorchester, Dorset, 1929 October 7 (Box 1)
  - Letters by Thomas Hardy, 1876–1927
    - Autograph letter, signed, to A. R. Andrews, Max Gate, 1902 January 7 (Box 1)
      Purchase, 1958.
    - Typed letter, signed, to Mr. Baring, [possibly Gerard Barry, editor of the Saturday Review ], Max Gate, Dorchester, Dorset, 1927 December 2 (Box 1)
    - Two autograph letters, signed, to James M. Barrie, Max Gate, 1917, 1924; 1924 (Box 1)
      Scope and Contents
      The letter of 1917 is in Hardy's hand, but is signed Th: & F. Hardy. The letter of 1924 introduces Serge Youriévitz.
      Source unknown.
    - Two autograph letters, signed, to Walter Besant, London and Dorchester, 1879, 1899; 1899 (Box 1)
      Gift, 1956.
    - Autograph letter, signed, to William Black, London, 1876 May 16 (Box 1)
      Photograph of Hardy enclosed.
      Gift, 1953.
    - Autograph letter, signed, to Mrs. Boucicault, Hyde Park Mansions, W., [19]06 June 16 (Box 1)
      Letterhead: The Athenaeum, Pall Mall, S. W.
    - Two autograph letters, signed, to A. M. Broadley, Max Gate, 1908 February (Box 1)
      Removed from volumes 2 and 3 of his The Dynasts, London, 1906-1908.
      Gift, 1935.
    - Autograph letter, signed, to A. M. Broadley, Max Gate, 1911 March 19 (Box 1)
      Removed from his Time's Laughing- stocks, 1909.
      Gift, 1915.
    - Autograph letter, signed, to Dr. Arnaldo Cervesato, Max Gate, Dorchester, 1901 June 20 (Box 1)
      Purchase, 1985.
    - Three autograph letters, signed, to Chatto and Windus, London, 1878 (Box 1)
      Accompanied by 8 receipts, signed by Hardy, for payments to Hardy from Chatto & Windus.
      Gift, 1971.
    - Autograph letter, signed, to Mrs. Champ Clark, Max Gate, Dorchester, 1918 August 18 (Box 1)
      Tollett and Harman Catalogue 1, page describing letter enclosed. Copy sent to Michael Millgate.
      Purchase, 1986.
    - Autograph letter, signed (with initials) to [Edward] Clodd, [1909 May 27?] (Box 1)
      With autograph letter, signed, from Clodd to unidentified, [19]09 May 27 on page 4.
      Gift, 1990.
    - Autograph letter, signed, to Lady Cynthia Colville, Max Gate, Dorchester, 1923 May 14 (Box 1)
    - Autograph letter, signed, to James Curle, Max Gate, 1913 January 30 (Box 1)
      Removed from his The Dynasts ... London and New York, Macmillan, 1903, vol. 1.
      Gift, 1974.
    - Autograph letter, signed, to Mr. De Lafontaine, Max Gate, Dorchester, 1894 December 2 (Box 1)
    - Postcard to W.A. Fisher (Box 1)
      See: Oversize, Box 4, folder 56
    - Autograph postcard, signed, to Miss M. Fletcher, Max Gate, Dorchester, 1903 May 8 (Box 1)
      Purchase, 1997.
    - Autograph letter, signed, to Mrs. Franklyn, London, 1879 March 26 (Box 1)
      Purchase, 1970.
    - Autograph letter, signed with initials, to Edmund Gosse, Max Gate, Dorchester, 1912 September 4 (Box 1)
      Removed from F.A. Hedgcock's Essai de critique, Thomas Hardy, penseur et artiste ... Paris [1911].
      Transfer, 1969.
    - Two notes, one typewritten, to Harley Granville-Barker, Max Gate, 1914 (Box 1)
    - Two autograph letters, signed, to Austin Harrison, Max Gate, 1913 (Box 1)
      Gift, 1975.
    - Autograph letter, signed, to Ford Maddox Hueffer, Max Gate, 1908 November 7 (Box 1)
      Purchase, 1983.
    - Autograph letter, signed, to the editor of La Vogue, 1899 July 12 (Box 1)
      Gift, 1960.
    - Eight autograph letters, signed, to Arthur Locker, editor of the Graphic, concerning the publication of Tess of the d'Urbervilles and A Group of Noble Dames, 1889–1891 (Box 1)
      Accompanied by two leaves of directions, in the hand of Mrs. Emma Hardy, for the weekly parts of Tess. Bound in full brown morocco.
      Also includes: 1) Postcard, signed, to W.A. Fisher, Max Gate, 1890 Dec 31.
      2) Heaton, J. A. Autograph letter, signed, to Arthur Locker concerning terms to be offered by the Graphic for Thomas Hardy's Tess of the d'Urbervilles, London, 1889 November 21.
      3) Autograph letter, signed, to William Algernon Locker, assistant editor of the Graphic, concerning the publication of Tess of the d'Urbervilles, Max Gate, 1890 December 31.
      Accompanied by 'directions for the first three weekly parts' of Tess, in the hand of Mrs. Emma Hardy.
    - Autograph letter, signed, to William Algernon Locker (Box 1)
    - Autograph letter, signed, to his publishers [Messrs. Sampson Law and Marston?], Wimborne, Dorset, 1882 November 27 (Box 1)
      Removed from volume 1 of Two on a Tower, London, 1882.
    - Four autograph letters, signed, to J. W. Mackail, Max Gate, 1916–1924 (Box 1)
      Discusses Shakespeare, Milton and John Bunyan's Pilgrim's Progress.
    - Autograph letter, signed, to Angus Maclachlan, Dorchester, 1910 December 20 (Box 1)
      Concerning the musical setting of one of Hardy's poems.
    - Autograph letter, signed, to J. Harold Napier, Max Gate, Dorchester, 1896 December 3 (Box 1)
    - Autograph letter, signed, to Henry Wood Nevinson, Dorchester, 1911 May 10 (Box 1)
      Purchase, 1984.
    - Autograph letter, signed, to H. W. Nevinson, Max Gate, 1916 March 31 (Box 1)
      Gift, 1963.
    - Note, unsigned, giving permission to Cecil Palmer to publish Jezreel, Max Gate, 1918 October 15 (Box 1)
      Purchase, 1975.
    - Autograph letter, signed, to [Rev. Thomas Perkins], Max Gate, [19]12 Dec 24 (Box 1)
    - Autograph letter, signed, to Mr. Powys, Dorchester, 1918 July 10 (Box 1)
      Purchase, 1990.
    - Five autograph letters, signed, to [Charles] S. Prideaux, Max Gate, Dorchester, [18]97-1912 (Box 1)
      On verso of letter of 1898 March 2: draft reply from C[harles] S. Prideaux. [1898] Mar 17.
    - Autograph letter, signed, and typed letter, signed, to Leonard Rees, Dorchester, 1922 (Box 1)
      Gift, 1957.
    - Autograph letter, signed, to Clement Shorter, Max Gate, [Dorchester], 1912 December 16 (Box 1)
      With Hardy's What the Shepherd Saw autograph manuscript fragment, 1881; autograph notes in red ink and Red Cross stamp on item. On wrapper: Hardy's What the Shepherd Saw autograph note signed, undated, explains this is the remaining 3 pages of the original manuscript.
      Gift, 1984.
    - Two postcards and telegram to Clement Shorter (Box 1)
      See: Series II, Box 2, folder 48
    - Autograph letter, signed, to Reginald Smith (Box 1)
    - Autograph letter, signed, to Mrs. Strang, Max Gate, Dorchester, 1910 January 24 (Box 1)
    - Autograph letter, signed, to [Arthur] Symons, Max Gate, 1906 August 26 (Box 1)
      Removed from Jude the Obscure.
    - Autograph letter, signed, to [G. M.] Trevelyan, Max Gate, Dorchester, 1909 May 25 (Box 1)
    - Postcard, signed, to Reginald Turner, London, 1910 June 6 (Box 1)
    - Autograph letter, signed, to [Frederick Whelen?], Max Gate, Dorchester, 1900 [October] 24 (Box 1)
      Purchase, 1993.
    - Autograph letter, signed, to "My dear Sir," Savile Club, 15, Savile Road. W., 1878 October 23 (Box 1)
    - Purchase, 1996. (Box 1)
    - Two autograph letters, signed, to two unidentified recipients, Max Gate, Dorchester, 1890; 1899 (Box 1)
  - Letters by J. A. Heaton, undated
    - Autograph letter, signed, to Arthur Locker, undated (Box 1)
- Writings by Thomas Hardy, 1873–1919; Series II
  - And There Was a Great Calm typescript of the poem, with autograph manuscript corrections, 1918 November 11 (Box 1)
    Removed from his And There Was a Great Calm, London 1920.
    Purchase, 1962.
  - Candour in English Fiction from The New Review, No. 8, with manuscript annotations, London, 1890 January (Box 1)
  - Dorset in London, typescript, original, corrected and revised by the author, London, 1908 (Box 1)
    First published in the Year Book of the Society of Dorset Men in London.
    Purchase, 1992.
  - England to Germany, etc., four poems with manuscript corrections, 1917 February (Box 1)
    Poems include: England to Germany, The Pity of It, I Met a Man, A New Year's Eve in War Time. Bound copy is one of 25 made for Florence Emily Hardy by Chiswick Press, London. Also includes:
    1) Two postcards to Clement Shorter, Max Gate, Dorchester, 1899 December 26 and 1915 October 24.
    2) Telegram to Clement Shorter, Dorchester, 1916 December 19, with envelope.
    Gift. Source unknown.
  - Far from the Madding Crowd, autograph manuscript, bound, [1873-1874] (Box 2)
    Autograph letter, signed by Hardy to Reginald Smith (1918 January 23), tipped in. Autograph letter, signed, by Mrs. Hardy to A. Edward Norton (1918 August 4) laid in.
    Gift, 1986.
  - Human shows, Far Phantasies, Songs, and Trifles, manuscript and typescript, corrected, undated (Box 2)
    Bound in dark blue morocco and tooled in gilt by Riviére.
    Gift.
  - Memories of Church Restoration: page sheets extracted from The Society for the Preservation of Ancient Buildings' Report of General Meeting, with manuscript annotations and corrections, London, 1906 (Box 3)
  - Reminiscences of a Dancing Man: autograph manuscript, 1895 (Box 3)
  - To Meet or Otherwise, autograph manuscript poem signed by Hardy, [1919] (Box 3)
    Bound in red morocco. Published in his Satires of Circumstance, London, 1919.
  - What the Shepherd Saw, autograph manuscript fragment, 1881 (Box 3)
    See: Series I, Box 1, folder 37
- Other Materials, 1889–1920; Series III
  - Photograph of Thomas Hardy in academic costume, taken by Bernard Griffin, 1920, and signed by Hardy, circa 1920 (Box 3)
    Gift, 1958.
- Oversize, 1889–1891
  - Eight autograph letters, signed, to Arthur Locker, editor of the Graphic, concerning the publication of Tess of the d'Urbervilles and A Group of Noble Dames, 1889–1891 (Box 4)
  - Autograph album pages, undated (Box 4)
    Two items. Album leaves with portraits of Thomas Hardy and autograph clippings mounted. With: Autograph letter, signed, to Alfred Parsons, Dorchester, 1884 March 15.
- Additions Since July 1997, 1885–1989; Series IV
  - Letters by Thomas Hardy, 1885–1925
    - Autograph letter, signed, to the artist W. P. Frith, 1896 March 12 (Box 5)
      From Max Gate, Dorchester.
    - Autograph letter, signed, to R. R. Bowker, 1880 August 12 (Box 5)
      From 1 Arundel Terrace, Trinity Road, Upper Tooting.
    - Autograph postcard, signed, to James Ripley Osgood, 1890 January 14 (Box 5)
    - Autograph letter, signed, to [R. A.] Scott-James concerning Modernism and Romance, [1909] (Box 5)
      Gift, 1997.
    - Autograph letter, signed, to "Dear Sir" enclosing a photograph of Hardy (not present), 1891 August 29 (Box 5)
    - Autograph letter, signed, to "Dear Sir" concerning plans to meet "Mr. Hueffer" for tea, 1910 July 7 (Box 5)
    - Autograph letter, signed, to Mrs. Lucas thanking her for her gift of etchings, 1925 December 10 (Box 5)
    - Autograph letter, signed, to [T. Wemyss Reid] thanking him for his magazine articles, 1891 February 2 (Box 5)
    - Five autograph letters to Frederic d'Erlanger, 1892 August-October (Box 5)
      Three autograph letters, signed, and two autograph postcards, signed, discussing d'Erlanger's plans for an opera version of Tess of the d'Urbervilles, including Hardy's formal grant of permission and comments on the libretto by Illica.
      Purchase, 1999.
    - Typed letter, signed, to the President, Vice-President, and Members of the Dorchester Debating Society, 1914 March 5 (Box 5)
      Thanks the members for a "charming gift" (cake-basket and album). Includes a typed letter, signed, from Florence Hardy, 1914 March 5, also thanking society for gift.
    - Autograph letter, signed, to "Dear Sirs" declining to contribute to a new magazine, 1894 October 24 (Box 5)
    - Autograph letter, signed, thanking the marine painter [Herbert or John] Everett for copies of portraits and sending a book of his in exchange, 1903 October 17 (Box 5)
    - Autograph letter, signed, to Mr. Crawfurd, 1895 February 1 (Box 5)
      Declines to contribute to Crawfurd's new magazine because he is fully occupied with the "long serial novel" in Harper's ( Jude the Obscure ) and with work on the complete edition of his fiction.
      Purchase, 2000.
    - Autograph postcard, signed, to J. F. Muirhead, 1901 April 10 (Box 5)
      Thanks him for forwarding a copy of Le Siecle. Accompanied by an engraved portrait of Hardy, signed by Hardy.
    - Letter to "My dear Sir" [John Bowen], 1885 December 10 (Box 5)
      Thanks him for a telegram and explains that publication of "the story" [ The Woodlanders ] has been postponed.
    - Letter to J. S. Udal, 1920 November 23 (Box 5)
      Thanks him for the loan of an article on the "charms and spells" of Dorset. Date appears in supplied docket.
    - Autograph letter, signed, to Susan Cunnington, 1902 June 17 (Box 5)
      Gives her permission to quote Rome: At the Pyramid of Cestius.
      Purchase, 2001.
    - Letter to "Miss Featherstonhaugh", undated (Box 5)
      Autograph letter, signed, returning a manuscript.
      Purchase, 1998.
    - Letter to "Dear Sir", 1911 December 10 (Box 5)
      Autograph note, signed, answering an inquiry about an orchard used by smugglers. From Max Gate, Dorchester.
    - Letter to Lord Frederic Hamilton, 1894 April 29 (Box 5)
      Autograph letter, signed, declining to speak on "literature" at a dinner. From 16 Pelham Crescent, South Kensington.
    - Letter to Miss [Hilda] Gorst, 1891 February 6 (Box 5)
      Autograph letter, signed, thanking her for compliment on "the story" and hoping she will like the next. From Max Gate, Dorchester.
    - Letter to "Dear Sir", 1908 February 10 (Box 5)
      Autograph note, signed, offering to discuss with Alfred Herbert Evans his ideas for a dramatization of The Trumpet Major. Possibly to Henry Austin Martin, Secretary of the Dorchester Debating and Dramatic Society.
  - Letters by Florence Emily Hardy, undated
    - Autograph letter, signed, to Eneas MacKay, Max Gate, Dorchester, [?] September 19 (Box 5)
      1 item (1 leaf); 18 cm. Thanking him for his gift of "an interesting book" and mentioning her donation of a portrait of Thomas Hardy. With: Wax seal on paper, labeled "The Seal of Thomas Hardy," stamped "Aug 25 1916."
  - Letters and Writings by Thomas Hardy (addition), 1885–1925
    - Autograph letter, signed, to "Dear Sir," Max Gate, near Dorchester, 1885 August 18 (Box 5)
      1 item (2 leaves); 18 cm. Letter to Percy Bunting declining to write an article on "the Laborours" for the Contemporary Review. With typed transcript.
    - Tess of the D'Urbervilles. A Tragedy in Four Acts and a Fore and After-Scene, [1925] (Box 5)
      Typescript, corrected, signed, of Hardy's dramatization of the novel. Wrapper stamped: "Please return to Curtis Brown Ltd. 116 West 39th St. New York City." Manuscript stitched. With typed letter, signed, from Hardy to Curtis Brown, Ltd., 1925 January 6. Accompanied by autograph letter, signed, from Gertrude Bugler to "Mr. Allan," 1928 October 24; typed letter, signed, and typed envelope from Richard Purdy to Frederick Baldwin Adams, Jr., 1946 February 17; and catalogue entry, annotated by Frederick Baldwin Adams, Jr., undated. Housed in a quarter morocco blue slipcase, gilt title on spine. Bookplate: Frederick Baldwin Adams, Jr.
      Purchase, 2002.
    - Autograph letter, signed, to Henry Symonds, Max Gate, Dorchester, 1905 February 24 (Box 5)
      1 item; 18 cm. Answering a letter from Symonds on a remark on "the charm of the Middle Ages." Discusses the emotional attractions of faith, but points out "a thing being unpleasant does not make it untrue." With a typed letter, signed, from Richard L. Purdy to A. A. S. Symonds, 1978 Apr 15; manuscript notes on Henry Symonds, undated; photocopy of published text of the letter; and advertising matter, undated.
    - Typed letter, signed, to Max Pemberton, Max Gate, Dorchester, 1918 December 13 (Box 5)
      1 item; 26 cm. Refusing to assist Pemberton in teaching short story writing. "Indeed it is a question whether storytelling can be taught at all..." From the library of Frederick B. Adams, Jr.
    - Typed letter, signed, to Arthur Symons, Max Gate, 1908 March 11 (Box 5)
      1 item; 26 cm. Thanking him for reading The Dynasts and discussing the appropriateness of "poetic diction" for historical characters, with reference to Shakespeare. Accompanied by typed transcript. From the library of Frederick B. Adams, Jr.
    - Autograph letter, signed, to Walter Besant, 20 Monmouth Road, Bayswater, [1889] June 28 (Box 5)
      1 item; 18 cm. Concerning the Society of Authors.
      Purchase, 2003.
    - Autograph postcard, signed, to Halliwell Sutcliffe, Max Gate, Dorchester, 1910 July 27 (Box 5)
      1 item; 9 cm. Thanking him for his congratulations.
  - 2002 Additions, 1893-1908, 1989; 1989; .42
    - Spectre of the Real typescripts and proofs, 1893-1894, 1989; 1989; 5 (Box 6)
      Two typescript proofs, with manuscript corrections. Accompanied by notes on Spectre of the Real by Pamela Dalziel.
    - Spectre of the Real galley proofs for the first printing, with manuscript corrections, circa 1893; 4 (Box 7)
    - Trumpet Major carbon copy of a manuscript of an adaptation by Alfred H. Evans, with printed programs and a manuscript note by Frederick Baldwin Adams, Jr. laid in, circa 1908; 3 (Box 6)
    - Catalogue of an Exhibition of Water-Colours of Wessex (Thomas Hardy's Country), by Walter Tyndale, With an Introductory Letter from Mr. Thomas Hardy, 1905 July (Box 6)
      Printed catalog, accompanied by an autograph note, signed, from Hardy to Tyndale, 1905.